so now let's consider how different lock
implementations
interact with the coherence protocol and
what performance do they achieve
let's look at three cores
0 1 and 2. let's first try to do this
with atomic exchange instructions core 0
let's say tries to grab the lock first
and it succeeds it does an atomic
exchange gets that the lock was free the
lock var is now going to be in the
modified state in the cache of course 0
and it's going to not be
present in core 1 and core 2's caches
now eventually core 0 which grab the
lock
will unlock by writing 0 to the lock var
but the question is what happens
meanwhile on core 1 and core 2.
both core 1 and core 2 might want to
also enter the same critical section
let's say core 1 tries first it does an
exchange of r1 and lock war
see that lock war is one so it didn't
grab the lock but because there was a
right to lock var
there is a
transfer of lock wire into this cache
where it's now modified and now
lockvar is invalid in core zeros cache
let's say that core zero now does its
own exchange does the same thing
tries to grab the lock sees that it's
one we'll try again but because it did
the right to lock where now it grabs the
block in the modified state and core one
gets it in invalid state and in core
zero it stays invalid and now as long as
the lock is busy these two will be
spinning in that loop so what's going to
happen is this block will move many many
times between their caches each time
causing communication on the shared bus
and each time spending a lot of power
none of this activity here will actually
succeed in grabbing the lock until the
lock var becomes zero
so at some point
let's say that core one was the last one
to grab the lock at the point where
clockwise written to zero this right
will cause yet another movement of the
block it becomes modified in core zeros
cache now and now whoever tries to grab
the lock first will succeed
by obtaining the block
writing to it but this time grabbing the
lock so if core 1 now succeeds in
grabbing the lock after it became
available core 2 continues this activity
further
so there is a lot of this going on as
long as anybody is waiting on a lock
this is very power hungry because these
movements of data between caches are
going to cost us a lot of energy per
transfer
and also
this activity here keeps the
interconnect between the cores busy for
example the shared bus
so the one core that is actually doing
useful work here while this is going on
if it has a cache miss will now be
slower in handling this cache miss
because it has to wait for the busy bus
that these two are keeping busy so not
only is it power hungry to do this it
also
by busy waiting in such an active way
we're slowing down the useful work that
is the only thing that can really result
in us actually getting the lock
eventually